Name: David Otieno Ogol

. P.o Box 3603-00100,

Nairobi, Kenya

ogoldave96@gmail.com

Mobile Number: +254729386937

Marital status: Married

Nationality: Kenyan

Date of Birth:25th November 1990

PROFILE SUMMARY

A process-oriented and, results-driven Quality Assurance officer, standards development expert, quality auditing skills and safety and health professional who has a passion for excellence. I have experience of working on the production of a wide variety of manufactured goods and possess a successful track of determining whether products meet expected standards. I have technical mind that excels when being challenged and possess an entrepreneurial spirit along with a successful track record of ensuring the timeliness, quality and accuracy of a production process. As a highly motivated individual I can effectively execute the essential duties and responsibilities of this post. My key strengths include conducting quality control activities and ensuring compliance with legal specifications. In addition to this I have experience of using the laboratory equipment and tools having been trained by the Kenya Bureau of standards, and association of medical engineers in Kenya.

EDUCATION

<u>Feb 2019-November 2019</u>: Certificate-Occupational Safety and Health-International Safety Training Centre(Nairobi)

2010-2012: Diploma in Analytical Chemistry; Kisumu national polytechnic

2009(May)-2009(November): Kenya Certificate of secondary Education-Barding secondary school(C+).

2005-2008: Kenya Certificate of secondary Education-St. Mary's High school, Yala(C+)

1998-2004: Kenya Certificate of Primary Education-Karapul primary school(B+)

Areas of Experience; Quality assurance, health and safety, audit and Customer complaints response

Key Skills and Competencies; Experience of working within a quality management system in the manufacturing, fully conversant with all relevant quality assurance procedures and audit skills.

Strengths: Attention to detail, time management, problem-solving, multitasking ability to work as part of a team and knowledge of quality standards.

WORK EXPERIENCE

March 2021-Date: Assistant Quality Assurance Manager: -Safepak Group of Companies(Nairobi) Responsibilities;

- Manage the HACCP program for the facility including internal and external warehouse audits, supplier quality and product control, manage all investigations, corporate compliance and quality assurance programs, as well as intergovernmental relations and day-to-day operations.
- Update and compose new HACCP plans, GMP, and SOP's to ensure that they meet accepted food safety principles, maintain historical records for documents pertaining to the QMS and ISO compliance.
- Maintain, control and conduct maintenance of the QMS, HACCP document to reflect additions, deletions, or amendments, play a key role in ISO auditing
- Review process consistency base on statistical process control (SPC) and techniques, maintain accurate records in accordance with cGMP regulations
- Conduct training programs on statistical process control (SPC)to upgrade the capabilities of the supplier, supervise daily quality assurance duties which include a staff of 37 in the facility.
- Review departmental Quality management system(QMS) metrics and integrate trend analyses on monthly basis; providing summaries for management, lead center review of findings, coordination of remediation (CAPA), if need and successful closure of audits timely.
- Complete all operations prior to their deadline by monitoring operations, recognizing weaknesses and ensuring compliance of procedures, Redesign QA job responsibilities, increasing oversight of critical manufacturing process and fulfilling Safepak commitment without increasing head count.
- Develop procedures for the emergency response and crisis management including physical security, information protection, incident management and investigation units, assist with protocols and other experimental projects to help troubleshoot and identify specific patterns and occurrences of defects affecting departments, developing and driving continuous improvement initiatives.

<u>February 2020-Date: -National technical committee member (Standards development technical Expert-Non-Management)-Kenya Bureau of standards (KEBS/TC-006-Edible nuts and seeds and KEBS/TC-023-Alcoholic beverages).</u>

Responsibilities;

- Providing technical support to technical committee on matters quality, safety, risk management and assessment, Collection and analysis of technical information for the drafting of the relevant standard as per the ISO guidelines.
- Attending and actively participating in committee meetings, commenting on public review, drafts and balloting on draft Kenyan Standards.
- Keeping respective organizations/institutions well informed about current standards developments, projects and expressing organizations/institutions views.
- Keeping respective organizations/institutions well informed about current standards developments, projects and expressing organizations/institutions views.
- Participating in regional and international standardization work by attending meetings, commenting and voting on regional and international draft standards.

<u>February 2020-February 2021: Senior Laboratory Analyst:-Diamond Industries Limited (Panga Company-Mombasa)</u>

Responsibilities;

- Analyze process samples and final products in a timely manner in order to accommodate the needs of the refinery.
- Verify all data before reporting information to ensure the quality of the data, coordinate sample
 and product testing with other technicians in order to improve turnaround time for reporting all
 data.
- Prioritize work based on the needs of the refinery, perform special tests like iodine value, peroxide value, free fatty acid content, acid value levels among other tests as required or requested.
- Perform routine maintenance and troubleshooting for instrumentation to achieve maximum equipment availability, maintain and update laboratory supply inventory to ensure continuity and safety of work.
- Explain verbally to relief all relevant information about the refinery, i.e. unit specifications
 and upsets, off-spec results, samples in progress and instrument problems, manage all
 investigations concerning non-conforming products complaints from the clients/customers
 and coordination of remediation (CAPA).
- Participate in relevant training events to increase personal development, maintain a clean work environment to promote health, safety, and work efficiency in the lab.
- Stored all retained samples according to Basic Practice procedures, transfer hazardous waste and empty solvent and reference fuel drums to the warehouse for proper disposal and supervised daily quality assurance duties which included a staff of 7 in the facility.

Feb 2020-January 2019: Senior Food Analyst: AgriQ quest Laboratories-Nairobi

Responsibilities;

DAVID OTIENO OGOL CV

- Analyze samples from the field and clients to ensure compliance with KEBS specifications and company specifications in a timely manner in order to release the test results within the specified turnaround time.
- Ensure functionality of equipment by checking Statistical Quality Controls(SQC's) and periodic calibration and maintenance, observe expiration dates and low reagent volumes to ensure adequate resources are available for all testing.
- Perform routine maintenance and troubleshooting for instrumentation to achieve maximum
 equipment availability like HPLC.GC-MS UV-Vis spectroscopy and Atomic Absorption
 spectroscopy, maintain and update laboratory supply inventory to ensure continuity and safety of
 work.
- Developing and maintaining an effective maintenance program and protocols for laboratory instrumentation, performing and/or coordinating with outside labs routine and specialized testing.
- Coordinating the development and implementation of quality control procedures to monitor
 the process control of Laboratory operations, overseeing operation of the Laboratory Information
 Management System (LIMS) including any necessary troubleshooting, as well as reporting
 preliminary and final batch reports to customers.
- Developing new, and modifying existing, analytical procedures to assist the laboratory in
 providing accurate and precise analyses to support refinery goals, performing quality assurance
 work in adherence to the Laboratory Quality Assurance Program to provide technically sound
 results to Laboratory customers, responsible for the safety/health of self and those working with,
 promoting health and safety of others, and performing quality work in a safe and environmentally
 conscientious manner.
- Training new lab personnel on lab analytical methods and other procedures

May2015-January 2019: Quality: Control officer: Coca Cola Beverages Africa-Equator Bottlers Limited-Kisumu.

Responsibilities;

- Responsible for complying with Company policies and procedures, established standards, and governmental regulations.
- Consulting with Laboratory leadership team, process supervisors, Engineers, and Unit Operators on non-compliance issues on the products. Providing technical assistance for project work and/or operational problems dealing with chemistry and/or instrumental analyses.
- Performing required quality control activities to ensure that products (both carbonated, oncarbonated soft drinks and manufactured packaging products) meet the specified quality parameters.
- Documenting, tracking and reporting on calibration status and maintenance activities.
- Monitor operations to ensure that they meet production standards, recommend adjustments to the assembly or production process
- Inspect, test, or measure materials or products being produced, remove all products and materials that fail to meet specifications, report inspection and test data such as weights, temperatures, grades, moisture content, and quantities inspected

August 2013-April 2015: Laboratory Analyst-United Millers Limited(Kisumu)

Responsibilities;

- Laboratory information management system use and fit for purpose verification, wheat and maize milling raw materials and products inspection and analysis
- Mill process control and quality analysis, Aflatoxins quantification data analysis skills and correlation establishments and trends establishments necessary for production decision making
- Packaging materials and finished products inspection where I gained strong market needs establishments and marketing gaps unmasking for exploitation while ensuring quality and legal compliance standards
- Customer complains expert accompanied with strong root cause analysis skills for a long lasting problem solving.
- Quality analysis using modern instrumentation. with strong trouble shooting skills and broad
 analytical work instruction and work manual adherence to ensure production quality is
 maintained, Aflatoxins quantification where and stock accounting as well as trend analysis and
 data presentation skills using Microsoft office including excel and word.

<u>January 2013-June 2013:</u> <u>Laboratory technician(Intern)-Kenya Bureau of standards(Nairobi)</u> Responsibilities;

- Analyze samples either collected or provided using laboratory equipment to determine the physical and chemical properties
- Receiving, labeling and analyzing samples (food, toxic, chemical and Agriculture) Processing samples submitted for analysis using automated and manual techniques leading to provision of accurate results.
- Organize the daily workload to ensure prioritization of critical cases including notification and discussion of results with senior officers to ensure provision of a reliable service.
- Prepare solutions, reagents, equipment, apparatus and accessories and other supplies needed at the lab.
- Utilize good laboratory practice to prevent cross-contamination and inaccurate results, clean, sterilize and maintain equipment and apparatus used in all tests and analysis.

<u>January 2011-April 2011:</u> Laboratory Technician(Attachment)<u>-Kenya Bureau Of Standards</u> Kisumu.

Responsibilities;

- Analyze samples either collected or provided using laboratory equipment to determine the physical and chemical properties
- Receiving, labeling and analyzing samples (food, toxic, chemical and Agriculture) Processing samples submitted for analysis using automated and manual techniques leading to provision of accurate results.
- Organize the daily workload to ensure prioritization of critical cases including notification and discussion of results with senior officers to ensure provision of a reliable service.
- Prepare solutions, reagents, equipment, apparatus and accessories and other supplies needed at the lab.
- Utilize good laboratory practice to prevent cross-contamination and inaccurate results, clean, sterilize and maintain equipment and apparatus used in all tests and analysis.

TRAININGS/CERTIFICATIONS

- <u>December 2020:</u> Internal auditor against ISO/IEC 17025:2017(General requirements for the competence of testing and calibration laboratories) and ISO 19011:2018(Guideline for auditing management system)-KENAS
- November 2020: Implementation course against ISO/IEC: 17025:2017(General requirements for the competence of testing and calibration laboratories)-KENAS
- October 2020: Introduction to HACCP: Food Safety Works
- Internal Auditor against ISO 9001:2015 (Quality management system)-KEBS
- Internal Auditor against ISO 22000:2018(Food safety management system)-KEBS
- Leader Auditor against ISO 22000:2018(Food safety management system)-KEBS
- Chemical safety and vulnerability assessment training; Kenya Chemical Society (July 2017)

Membership to Professional bodies;

- <u>Affiliate</u> member of the KEBS national quality institute; Member no; KEBS/NQI/M/PER/381
- <u>Affiliate</u> member of the Royal Society of chemistry; Membership no: <u>663059</u>
- Member of the Kenya Chemical society; Membership no:281
- Member of the international food safety and quality network.

Achievement; Participated as a panelist on the conversion of waste to Energy in Africa organized by Harvard University and the Agency for science technology information and communication(ASTICOM).

Referees:

1.Mr. Maurice Otieno

3. Mr. Jack Ronge

Quality Assurance Manager,

World class Manufacturing officer-Unilever Kenya

Safepak Group of companies

mobile; +254720737558

Mobile: +254722483403

email address; jack.ronge@unilever.com

Email address; maurice@ke.safepakgroup.com

2.Mrs Betty Nkatha

Senior standards development officer- Kenya Bureau of Standards

Mobile: +254721639728

4. Mrs. Brenda Chebet.

email address;nkathab@kebs.org

Supply chain development specialist Coca Cola Beverages Africa

email address:bchebet@ccbagroup.com

mobile; +254714100069